Guide to the Texas City disaster records, 1947-2003 MS 529
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Texas City disaster records
1947-2003
1947-1949
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Morris, Robert M.
MS 529
1.5 Linear Feet
The Texas City disaster records were created and / or maintained by survivor Robert M. Morris, of Texas City, TX. The reports, statements, images and notes describe the events of the April 16, 1947 when a French ship carrying fertilizer on Galveston Bay caught fire and exploded, causing disaster on shore at the nearby Monsanto styrene plant and other petroleum refineries, homes, warehouses, ships and buildings. At least 576 were killed and 4,000 injured, with the town being almost completely destroyed.
Historical Sketch
The worst industrial accident in U.S. history took place on the morning of April 16, 1947 when a French freighter carrying fertilizer (ammonium nitrate) on Galveston Bay caught fire and exploded, causing disaster on shore at the nearby Monsanto styrene plant and other petroleum refineries, homes, warehouses, ships and buildings. At least 576 were killed and 4,000 injured, with Texas City being almost completely destroyed.
Monsanto rebuilt the plant, which was only three years old, in order to help supply the nation's synthetic rubber needs during World War II. The plant was bought by Gordon Cain in 1986 and became known as Sterling Chemicals.
Correspondents include Robert M. Morris of Grantham, N.H.; William H. Lane of Texas City; John F. Jacobs of Nashville, TN; and Fred Ruecker. Lane survived the disaster. Morris was Monsanto's Assistant Plant Manager. After being thrown in a Jeep, trapped under it and nearly drowned by a tidal wave, Morris survived and went on to assist in the rescue efforts. Fred Ruecker lost his father, a plant engineer, in the disaster, as did John F. Jacobs. After surviving the disaster, Morris was transferred to Springfield, Massachusetts (1949) and then to St. Louis (1953), going on to eventually settled in New Hampshire.
Morris' daughter Susie Glasscock earned her BA in economics from Rice in 1962 and currently serves on the Rice Board of Trustees. Her husband Melbern Glasscock earned a BSME from Texas A&M in 1959 and his MS in mechanical engineering at Rice in 1961. Mr. and Mrs. Glasscock have been regular students of the School of Continuing Studies at Rice University for almost 30 years. In January 2006, the school was renamed the Susanne M. Glasscock School of Continuing Studies in honor of the Glasscock's endowment gift believed to be the largest endowment gift ever made to a university continuing education program in the United States.
Scope and Contents
The Texas City disaster records were created and / or maintained by survivor Robert M. Morris. The reports, statements, images and notes describe the events of the April 16, 1947 when a French freighter carrying fertilizer caught fire and exploded, causing disaster on shore at the nearby Monsanto petroleum plant and other refineries, homes, warehouses and buildings. At least 576 were killed and 4,000 injured, with the town being almost completely destroyed.
Original materials of note include Monsanto statements and reports and correspondence about the events. Two videotapes feature documentaries of the disaster. The History Channel documentary, "Eyes of Texas" (Houston KHOU-TV) segment and two Houston KTRC-TV News Channel 13 segments include first accounts from survivors, including Robert Morris and William Lane.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Restrictions on Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated by Susie Glasscock, 2007.
General note
Portions of this collection are available online at https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/21672.
Related Material
Mansanto Chemical Company archives located at Washington University Libraries, St. Louis, Missouri. Finding aid for this material is on-line at http://library.wustl.edu/units/spec/archives/guides/pdf/monsanto.pdf.
Index Terms
Subjects
Petroleum industry and trade; Industrial accidents; Fires; Oil and gas; Environment
Document Types
corrrespondence; clippings (information artifacts); newsletters; videotapes; photographs; reports
Places
Texas -- Texas City
Subjects (Persons)
Lane, William M.; Jacobs, John F.; Ruecker, Fred
Subjects (Corporations)
Monsanto Chemical Company; High Flyer (Ship); Grandchamp (Ship) -- Explosion, 1947; Wilson B. Keene (Ship)
- Series I: Statements, 1947-1948, 162903
  - R. M. Morris statements, 1947, 162905 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Monsanto statements, 1947-1948, 162904 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Reports, 1947, 162898
  - Monsanto Executive Committee report, May 1947, 162902 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Monsanto Dept. of Industrial & Public Relations Report, May 1947, 162901 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Oil Insurance Underwriters Report, June 1947, 162900 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fire Prevention & Engineering Bureau of Texas, and national Board of Fire Underwriters, undated report, 162899 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series III: Newsclippings, 1947-2003, 162896
  - 1947-2003, 162897 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series IV: Monsanto Chemical Co. plant history and personnel, 162891
  - Monsanto plant history, 1941-1965, 162895 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Personnel rosters, 1947 (annotated with information on the deceased and missing), 162894 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Personnel organizational charts, Texas Division, 1947-1948 (includes position titles and occupants' names, as well as notes "dead" and "safe"), 162893 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Monsanto Chemical Co. casualties, hospitalizations, widows and survivors, 1947, 162892 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series V: Correspondence, 1947, 1955 and 1997, 162889
  - Correspondence, 1947, 1955 and 1997, 162890 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    General note
    1947 correspondence includes an original account of the disaster by William Lane, and 1947 Monsanto newsletters; 1997 correspondence relates to anniversary events.
- Series VI: Anniversary events, 1997, 162886
  - Correspondence, flyers, brochures and ephemera regarding 1997 anniversary events in Texas City, 162888 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper coverage of 1997 anniversary, 162887 (Box 2, Folder -)
- Series VII: Maps and photographs, 162881
  - Site maps, 1947, 162885 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes a site map annotated with numbers relating to photographs, and an index to those photographs, but it is not clear if the largely unannotated photographs in this collection relate to this index.
  - Images, 1947 post-explosion (27 black and white 8x10s), 162884 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Images, circa. 1949 post-explosion (6 black and white 8x10s, 6 black and white postcards), 162883 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Images, oversize (5 black and white 11x14s), 162882 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series VIII: Video, 1957 & 1997 notes, 162876
  - Manuscript and typescript notes regarding "Texas City Film" and "Introduction to Safety Movie", 1952 with 1997 notes, 162880 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - VHS videotape "Texas City - 1997 Reviews" 20 minutes. Includes "Eyes of Texas" (Houston KHOU-TV Channel 2) segment and two Houston KTRC-TV News Channel 13 segments. Not for reproduction., 162879 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - VHS videotape "Texas City - History Channel" 45 minutes. Not for reproduction., 162878 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - DVD access copy of videotapes: "Texas City - 1997 Reviews" 20 minutes & "Texas City - History Channel" 45 minutes. Not for reproduction., 162877 (Box 2, Folder 4)